<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on TutorialEdge.net</title>
    <link>/series/blog/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on TutorialEdge.net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/series/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating to Hugo</title>
      <link>/post/blog/migrating-to-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2016 16:11:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/blog/migrating-to-hugo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve frequented this site in the past you should hopefully have noticed a huge change to the way the site looks and hopefully the speed at which the site serves content. Over the past 2 weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with a static site tool, similar to that of Jekyll, called Hugo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reasons-for-the-migration&#34;&gt;Reasons for the Migration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;ease&#34;&gt;Ease&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first and biggest reason I&amp;rsquo;m moving to a github based site is due to the ease with which I can make changes. I was writing in markdown with the old system so the writing style isn&amp;rsquo;t going to change and leveraging the power of github when it comes to revision history is fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;speed&#34;&gt;Speed&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laravel 5 is a great framework, I really respect what Taylor has been able to do with it but unfortunately I don&amp;rsquo;t have the time to custom build my own CMS anymore. Initially I went down that path in order to teach myself how to do it but my focus is shifting and I&amp;rsquo;d rather spend the time writing articles for the site than dealing with all the extra stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to site performance, I&amp;rsquo;m hoping that the new static method will improve the speed at which my site is delivered. Afterall, nothing can really beat a simple get request to already created html and css. With hugo I perform all the processing that would have been done on every page request right at the time of deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also no longer have to worry about managing a database and worrying about database performance. With Hugo, github essentially acts as the database and I don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about the latency for performing a lookup for a post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;community&#34;&gt;Community&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving to a public github based solution means that other people can actively contribute( should they wish) to the site and help make it one of the best online resources for technical tutorials. I&amp;rsquo;ve had multiple friends ask me if they could write and post things on it and with the current Laravel content management system, it would have been a complex process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>